My topic is handedness-whether in different sports it is better to be left-
or right-sided or whether a more balanced approach is more successful,
I'm left-handed myself and I actually didn't see any relevance to my own life
when I happened to start reading an article by a sports psychologist called Peter
Matthews.
He spent the first part of the article talking about handedness in music instead
of sport,
which I have to say almost put me off from reading further.
But what I soon became struck by was the sheer volume of both observation
and investigation he had done in many different sports and I felt persuaded that
what he had to say would be of real interest.
I think Matthews' findings will be beneficial, not so much in helping sportspeople to
work on their weaker side,
but more that they can help them identify the most suitable strategies to use
in a given game.
Although most trainers know how important handedness is, at present they are rather reluctant
to make use of the insights scientists like Matthews can give,
which I think is rather short-sighted because focusing on individual flexibility is only part
of the story.
Anyway, back to the article.
Matthews found a German study which looked at what he called 'mixed-handedness',
that is, the capacity to use both left and right hands equally.
It looked at mixed-handedness in 40 musicians on a variety of instruments.
Researchers examined a number of variables, e.g.
type of instrument played, regularity of practice undertaken and length of time playing instrument...
and found the following:
keyboard players had high levels of mixed-handedness, whereas string players like cellists
and violinists strongly favoured one hand.
Also those who started younger were more mixed-handed.
Matthews also reports studies of handedness in apes.
Apes get a large proportion of their food by 'fishing' ants from ant hills.
The studies show that apes, like humans, show handedness-though for them right-
and left-handedness is about equal, whereas about 85% of humans are right-handed.
Studies showed that apes consistently using the same hand fished out 30% more ants
than those varying between the two.
Matthews started researching several different sports and found different types of handedness in each.
By the way, he uses 'handedness' to refer to the dominant side for feet
and eyes as well as hands.
Anyway, his team measured the hand, feet and eyes of 2,611 players
and found that there were really three main types of laterality:
mixed-you work equally well on both sides-both hand and eye;
single-you tend to favour one side but both hand and eye favour the same
side;
and cross-laterality-a player's hands and eyes favour only one side
but they are opposite sides.
Let's start with hockey.
Matthews found that it was best to be mixed-handed-this is
because a hockey stick must be deployed in two directions-it would be a drawback to have hand
or eye favouring one side.
An interesting finding is that mixed-handed hockey players were significantly more confident than their
single-handed counterparts.
Things are slightly different in racket sports like tennis.
Here the important thing is to have the dominant hand
and eye on the one side.
This means that there is a bigger area of vision on the side where
most of the action occurs.
If a player is cross lateral the racket is invisible from the dominant eye
for much of the swing, it means that they can only make corrections much
later...
and often the damage has been done by then.
And moving to a rather different type of sport which involves large
but precise movements gymnastics.
It's been found that cross hand-eye favouring is best.
The predominant reason for this is because it aids balance which is of course
absolutely central to performance in this sport.